<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="wright-grammar.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI
  xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>A Grammar of the Arabic Language, translated from the German of Caspari, and edited with numerous additions and corrections</title>
        <author>William Wright</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Publication Information</p> 
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Information about the source</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl>
        <cRefPattern
          matchPattern="([0-9]+):([0-9]+)"
          replacementPattern="#xpath(//body/div1[$1]/div6[$2])"/>
      </refsDecl>    
      
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
        <pb n="v" facs="p0008.png"/>
        <div type="preface">
            <head>Preface to the third edition</head>
            <p>The Second Edition of Wright's Grammar of the Arabic language
            had been out of print long before the death of its author, but
            he was never able to find the leisure necessary for preparing a
            New Edition. The demand for it having become more and more 
            pressing, Prof. W. Robertson Smith, who well deserved the honour
            of succeeding to Wright's chair, resolved to undertake this 
            task. He bagan it with his usual ardour, but the illness which cut
            short his inevaluable life soon interrupted the work. At his death
            56 pages had been printed, whilst the revision had extended over 30
            pages more. Robertson Smith had made use of some notes of mine,
            which he had marked with my initials, and it was for this reason
            among others that the Syndics of the Cambridge University Press
            invited me, through Prof. Bevan, to continue the revision. After
            earnest deliberation I consented, influenced chiefly by my respect
            for the excellent work of one of my dearest friends and by a desire
            to complete that which another dear friend had begun. Moreover Prof.
            Bevan promised his assistance in correcting the English style and
            in seeing the book through the press.</p>
            <p>I have of course adhered to the method followed by Robertson
	    Smith in that part of the Grammar which he revised. Trifling 
	    corrections and additions and such suggestions as had already
	    been made by A. Mtiller, Fleischer and other scholars, are given
	    in square brackets. Only in those cases where it seemed necessary
	    to take all the responsibility upon myself, have I added my 
	    initials. Besides the printed list of additions and corrections at
	    the end of the Second Volume, Wright had noted here and there
	    <pb n="vi" facs="p0009.png" />on the margin of his own copy some 
	    new examples (chiefly fromthe Naḳāiḍ) which have been inserted, 
	    unless they seemed quite superfluous, without any distinctive sign. 
	    I have found but very few notes by Robertson Smith on the portion 
	    which he had not definitely revised ; almost all of these have been 
	    marked with his initials. Wright's own text has been altered in a 
	    comparatively small number of passages (for instance § 252, § 353),
	    where I felt sure that he would have done it himself. Once or twice 
	    Wright has noted on the margin " wants revision."</p>
	    <p>The notes bearing upon the Comparative Grammar of the Semitic 
	    languages have for the most part been replaced by references to 
	    Wright's Comparative Grammar, published after his death by 
	    Robertson Smith (1890).</p>
	    <p>I have to acknowledge my obligations to Mr Du Pré Thornton, who 
	    drew my attention to several omissions. But my warmest thanks must
	    be given to my dear friend and colleague Prof. Bevan, who has not 
	    only taken upon himself all the trouble of seeing this revised 
	    edition through the press, but by many judicious remarks has 
	    contributed much to the improving of it.</p>
	    <p>The Second Volume is now in the printers' hands.</p>
	    <closer>
	      <signed>M. J. de GOEJE.</signed>
	      <dateline>Leyden, February, 1896.</dateline>
	    </closer>
        </div>
        <pb n="vi" facs="p0009.png" />
	<div type="preface">
	  <head>Preface to the second edition.</head>
	  <p>A Second Edition of my revised and enlarged translation of
	  Caspari's Arabic Grammar having been called for, I have thought it 
	  my duty not simply to reprint the book, but to subject it again to a 
	  thorough revision. In fact, the present is almost a new work ; for 
	  there is hardly a section which has not undergone alteration, and 
	  much additional matter has been given, as the very size of this 
	  volume (351 pages instead of 257) shows.</p>
	  <p>In revising the book I have availed myself of the labours of Arab 
	  Grammarians, both ancient and modern. Of the former I may mention in 
	  particular the ʾAlfīya (اَلْأَفِيَّةُ) of ʾIbn Mālik, with the 
	  Commentary of ʾIbn Aḳīl (ed. Dieterici, 1851, and the Beirut edition 
	  of 1872); the Mufaṣṣal (اَلْمُفَصَّلُ) of ʾel-Zamahśarī (ed.Broch, 
	  1859) ; and the Lāmīyatu ʾl-Afʿāl (لَامِيَّةُ ٱلْأَفْعَالِ) of 
	  ʾIbn Mālik, with the Commentary of his son Badru ʾd-dīn (ed. 
	  Volck,1866). Of recent native works I have diligently used the 
	  Miṣbāḥu ʾl-Ṭālib fī Baḥṯi ʾl-Maṭālib 
		  (مِصْبَاحُ ٱلْطَّالِبِ فِي بَحْثِ ٱلْمَطَالِبِ),		
	  that is, the Baḥṯu ʾl-Maṭālib of the Maronite Gabriel Farḥāt, with the 
	  notes of Buṭrus ʾel-Bistānī (Beirut, 1854); ʾel-Bistānī's smaller 
	  Grammar, founded upon the above, entitled Miftāḥu ʾl-Misbāḥ 
	  (مِفْتَاحُ ٱلْمِصْبَاحِ, second edition, Beirut, 1867);
	  and Nāṣif ʾel-Yāziǵī's Faṣlu ʾl-H̱iṭāb
(فَصْلُ ٱلْخِطَابِ, second edition, Beirut,1866).
</p>
	  <p>Among European Grammarians I have made constant use ofthe works of 
	  S. de Sacy (Grammaire Arabe, 2de éd., 1831), Ewald (Grammatica 
	  Critica Linguaæ Arabicæ, 1831-33), and Lumsden (A Grammar of the 
	  Arabic Language, vol. i., 1813) ; which last,
	  <pb n="viii" facs="p0010.png" />however, is based on the system of the 
	  Arab Grammarians, and therefore but ill-adapted, apart from its bulk 
	  and rarity, for the use of beginners. I have also consulted with 
	  advantage the grammar of Professor Lagus of Helsingfors (Lärokurs i 
	  Arabiska Språket, 1869). But I am indebted above all to the labours 
	  of Professor Fleischer of Leipzig, whose notes on the first volume 
	  of De Sacy's Grammar (as far as p. 359) have appeared from time to 
	  time in the Berichte der Konigl. Sachsischen Gesellschaft 
	  der Wissenschaften (1863-64-66-70), in which periodical the 
	  student will also find the treatises of the same scholar Ueber einige 
	  Artender Nominal apposition im Arabischen (1862) and Ueber 
	  das Verhdltniss und die Construction der Sack- and Stoffworter 
	  im Arabischen (1856).</p>
	</div>
    </front>
    <body>

      <div type="volume" n="1">
        <div type="part" n="First">
          <head>Orthography and Orthoëpy</head>
          <div type="level3" n="I" xml:id="the-letters-as-consonants">
            <head>The Letters as Consonants</head>
            <div type="par" n="1"><p>
            Arabic, like Hebrew and Syriac, is written and read from 
            <milestone unit="letter" n="A"/> right to left. The letters of the
            alphabet ( ) are twenty-eight in, and are all consonants, though
            three of them are also used vowels (see § 3). They vary in form,
            according as they are connected with a preceding or following letter,
            and, for the most part, terminate in a bold stroke, when they stand
            alone or at the end of a word. The following Table gives the letters
            in their usual order, along with their names and numerical values.
            </p></div>
          </div>
        </div>
        <pb n="29" facs="p0047.png"/>
        <div type="part" n="Second">
          <head>Etymology or the Parts of Speech.</head>
          <div type="level3" n="I">
            <head>The Verb, <arabicWord>اَلْفِعْلُ</arabicWord>.</head>
            <milestone unit="letter" n="A"/>
            <div type="level4" n="A">
              <head>General View.</head>
              <div type="level5" n="1" xml:id="the-forms-of-the-triliteral-verb">
                <head>The Forms of the Triliteral Verb.</head>
                <div type="par" n="33"><p>The great majority of the Arabic verbs
                are triliteral (<term xml:lang="arb">ثُلَاثِيٌّ</term>), that is to 
                say, contain three radical letters, though quadriliteral 
                (<term xml:lang="arb">رُبَاعِيٌّ</term>) verbs are by no means rare.
                </p> </div>
                <div type="par" n="34"><p><milestone unit="letter" n="B"/>From 
                the first or ground-form of the triliteral and quadriliteral 
                verbs are derived in different ways several other forms, which 
                express various modifications of the idea conveyed by the first.
                </p></div>
                <div type="par" n="35"><p>The derived forms of the triliteral 
                verb are usually reckoned fifteen in number, but the learner may
                 pass over the last four, because (with the exception of the 
                 twelfth) they are of very rare occurrence.</p>
                  <list rend="col3" type="ordered" dir="rtl">
                    <label>I.</label>
                    <item>فَعَلَ</item>
                    <label>II.</label>
                    <item>فَعَّلَ</item>
                    <label>III.<milestone unit="letter" n="C"/></label>
                    <item>فَاعَلَ</item>
                    <label>IV.</label>
                    <item>أَفْعَلَ</item>
                    <label>V.</label>
                    <item>تَفَعَّلَ</item><cb/>
                    <label>VI.</label>
                    <item>تَفَاعَلَ</item>
                    <label>VII.</label>
                    <item>اِنْفَعَلَ</item>
                    <label>VIII.</label>
                    <item>اِفْتَعَلَ</item>
                    <label>IX.</label>
                    <item>اِفْعَلَّ</item>
                    <label>X.</label>
                    <item>اِسْتَفْعَلَ</item><cb/>
                    <label>XI.</label>
                    <item>اِفْعَالَّ</item>
                    <label>XII.</label>
                    <item>اِفْعَوْعَلَ</item>
                    <label>XIII.</label>
                    <item>اِفْعَوَّلَ</item>
                    <label>XIV.</label>
                    <item>اِفْعَنْلَلَ</item>
                    <label>XV.</label>
                    <item>اِفْعَنْلَى</item>
                  </list>
                  <div type="rem" n="a"><p><milestone unit="letter" n="A"/>
                    The <abbr>3d</abbr> <abbr>pers.</abbr> 
                    <abbr>sing.</abbr> <abbr>masc</abbr> <abbr>Perf.</abbr>,
                    being the simplest form of the verb, is commonly used as 
                    paradigm, but for shortness’ sake, we always render it into
                   English by the infinitive; <arabicWord>قَتَلَ<trans>to kill</trans>
                   </arabicWord>, instead of <trans>he has killed</trans>.</p></div>
                  <pb n="30" facs="p0048.png"/>
                  <div type="rem" n="b"><p>The arab grammarians use the verb 
                    <arabicWord>فَعَلَ</arabicWord>(<distinct xml:lang="he">פָעַל</distinct>)
                  as paradigm, whence the first radical of the triliteral verb is called
                  by them <arabicWord>اَلْفَآءُ<trans>the fā</trans></arabicWord>,
                    the second <arabicWord>اَلْعَيْنُ<trans>the ʿain</trans></arabicWord>,
                    and the third <arabicWord>اَللَّمُ<trans>the lām</trans></arabicWord>.</p></div>  
                  <div type="rem" n="c"><p>As the above order and numbering of the
                  conjugations are those adopted in all the European Lexicons, the learner
                  should note them carefully.
                  </p></div>
                </div>
                <div type="par" n="36"><p>the <term>first</term> or ground-form is
                generally transitive (<term xml:lang="arb">مُتَعَدٍّ</term>) or
                intransitive (<term xml:lang="arb">غَيْرُ مُتَعَدٍّ</term> or 
                <term xml:lang="arb">لَازمٌ</term>)
                in signification, according to the vowel which accompanies its
                second radical.</p></div>
                <div type="par" n="37"><p><milestone unit="letter" n="B"/>
                The vowel of the second radical is <emph>a</emph> in most of the 
                transitive, and not a few of the intransitive verbs; e.g.
                <arabicWord>ضَرَبَ<trans>to beat</trans></arabicWord>,
                <arabicWord>كَتَبَ<trans>to read</trans></arabicWord>,
                <arabicWord>قَتَلَ<trans>to kill</trans></arabicWord>, 
                <arabicWord>وَهَبَ<trans>to give</trans></arabicWord>;
                <arabicWord>ذَهَبَ<trans>to go away</trans></arabicWord>,
                <arabicWord>رَشَدَ<trans>to go the right way</trans></arabicWord>,
                <arabicWord>جَلَسَ<trans>to sit</trans></arabicWord>. 
                </p></div>
                <div type="par" n="38"><p>The vowel <emph>i</emph> in the same
                position has generally an intransitive signification, 
                <emph>u</emph> invariably so. The distinction between them is,
                that <emph>i</emph> indicates a temporary state or condition, or
                a merely accidental in persons or things; whilst <emph>u</emph>
                indicates a state, or a <milestone unit="letter" n="C"/> 
                naturally quality. E.g. 
                <arabicWord>فَرِحَ or جَذِلَ<trans>to be glad</trans></arabicWord>,
                <arabicWord>حَزِنَ<trans>to be sorry</trans></arabicWord>,
                <arabicWord>أَشِرَ or بَطِرَ<trans>to be proud and insolent</trans>
                </arabicWord>,
                <arabicWord>أَدِمَ<trans>to become whitish</trans></arabicWord>,
                <arabicWord>شَهِبَ<trans>to become gray</trans></arabicWord>,
                <arabicWord>سَلِمَ<trans>to be safe and sound</trans></arabicWord>,
                <arabicWord>مَرِضَ<trans>to be sick</trans></arabicWord>,
                <arabicWord>كَبِرَ<trans>to become old</trans></arabicWord>,
                <arabicWord>كَبِرَ<trans>to become old</trans></arabicWord>,
                <arabicWord>عَمِىَ<trans>to be blind</trans></arabicWord>;
                but <arabicWord>حَسُنَ<trans>to be blind</trans></arabicWord>,
                <arabicWord>قَبُحَ<trans>to be ugly</trans></arabicWord>,
                <arabicWord>ثَقُلَ<trans>to be heavy</trans></arabicWord>,
                <arabicWord>شَرُفَ<trans>to be high or noble
                <note place="bottom">Or <trans>to become noble</trans> for the 
                    form with <emph>u</emph> of the second radical often means 
                    <emph>to become what one was not before</emph>, 
                    Kāmil, p.415 –De G.</note></trans></arabicWord>,
                <arabicWord>سَفُلَ<trans>to be low or mean</trans></arabicWord>,
                <arabicWord>كَبُرَ<trans>to be large</trans></arabicWord>,
                <arabicWord>صَغُرَ<trans>to be small</trans></arabicWord>.
                </p>
                  <div type="rem" n="a"><p><milestone unit="letter" n="D"/>
                  Many verbs of the form فَعِلَ are transitive according to our 
                  way of thinking, and therefore govern the accusative,
                  e.g. <arabicWord>عَلِمَ<trans>to know (scire)</trans></arabicWord>,
                  <arabicWord>حَسِبَ<trans>to think</trans></arabicWord>,
                  <arabicWord>رَحِمَ<trans>to pity or have mercy upon</trans>
                  </arabicWord>, <arabicWord>سَمِعَ<trans>to hear</trans>
                  </arabicWord>.</p>
                  </div>
                <pb n="31" facs="p0049.png"/>
                  <div type="rem" n="b"><p><milestone unit="letter" n="A"/>
                    The same three forms occur in Hebrew and Aramaic, though
                    the distinction is in these languages no longer so clearly
                    marked. [See Comp. Gr. p. 165 seq.]
                    </p>
                  </div>
                </div>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div> <!-- I -->
        </div> <!-- part First -->
      </div> <!-- volume 1 -->
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
